Thank you.
Plaço do Comércio in Lisbon is where the Carnation Revolution began 50 years ago.
A turning point in Portugal's history being celebrated this year.
On the 25th of April 1974,
the Portuguese were finally free from dictatorship.
A day that
72-year-old Aurora Rodrigues will never forget.
Ah,
Mariana I'm going to the moon I'm going to the moon
How do you feel being here today?
It's the end of forgetting,
the end of erasing.
It frees me from the past.
Those who arrested me are no longer here.
Those who oppressed all these people are no longer here and they will not return.
You have already been jailed You have already been jailed You have already been jailed
The political police,
known as the PD,
brought her to this jail on the outskirts of Lisbon.
And I didn't speak,
I didn't say anything,
I just beat them.
Aurora's torturer was later posted to Africa and was never brought to justice.
Other members of the political police served just a few months in prison.
More than 30 years later,
I had the symptoms and a reaction.
I was stressed.
I couldn't hear noises.
Nobody could appear by my side without me waiting.
Everything made me panic.
30,000 Portuguese people were jailed by the regime.
Their liberation happened thanks to a handful of men.
Now known as the April Captains,
Carlos Matos Gomes was one of them.
It represents freedom,
it represents the strength of the land,
the strength of the youth.
And on the other hand,
we have the flag that the young officers of my generation fought for.
That fight began thousands of kilometres away from Portugal,
in the African colonies.
For six years,
Carlos went to wars on the three front lines of his country's colonies.
While the rest of Europe had already ended its colonisation,
Portugal was digging in.
The dictatorship of António Salazar used all its economic and human resources on preserving the empire,
an unpopular and dirty war.
140,000 men went to the front.
More than 10,000 never returned.
The guerrilla movements became stronger and stronger,
more well-organized.
The military was increasingly worse-instructed.
There was the demoralization of the prolonged wars.
While Carlos and his fellow soldiers were stationed to Africa,
back in Lisbon a plan hatched to overturn the regime.
So...
Rodrigo,
Souza and Castro and ten other captains planned the operation of the 25th of April.
For the first time ever,
soldiers restored Portugal's democracy.
For the first time,
in political democracy,
we had to present to the Portuguese people a political project consistent with our attitude of revolt.
And that political project was to break Portugal's isolation,
democratize the country,
take the people to the elections and integrate us in Europe.
The April captains know that democracy can never be taken for granted.
To make sure history isn't forgotten,
Aurora has decided to share her personal experience.
It's important because young people know very little about what happened,
what happened in the house.
Also because in Portugal the recent history of Portugal has not been given much importance.
How did they get the idea?
How did this group come about?
of posters,
of poems.
The posters that explain what it was like not being able to get sick because of the SNS and not having health conditions.
It was the one where you couldn't vote.
The boyfriends couldn't kiss on the street.
He came to the police.
He was indecent.
If these people were to kiss on the street,
if they were two men,
it would be unthinkable.
That was unthinkable for Salazar.
The ordinary behaviour of teens today would have been considered a threat to the stability of the regime.
I never beat anyone,
I never hurt anyone.
I was arrested because
I thought so.
And as I thought,
I had subversive ideas against the security of the State.
Thanks to Aurora,
the achievements of these Portuguese heroes will be remembered.
We must ensure that freedom is maintained in our country.
I think there will always be things and aspects that we can improve.
Nothing becomes perfect overnight.
And I think that as a generation that did not experience the 25th of
April, we have the obligation to try to maintain this freedom in our country and fight for all the people who sacrificed themselves so that it was possible for us to be free today.
Freedom was the dream of a whole generation of Portuguese people.
After a four-decade-long struggle,
the Salazar regime finally collapsed on this square.
Adelino Gomes was one of the few journalists who covered the event.
Thank you.
One day we met and you were here 50 years ago.
Hearing Grandola Bila Morena on the radio,
a revolutionary song banned by the dictatorship,
Adelino knew the coup d'etat had begun.
Leaving his microphone behind,
he rushed out of his home to meet the soldiers.
The objective was the General Quartel of the GPR,
the Republican
Guard. Here,
the President of the Council of Ministers had been resettled with some of his ministers.
He was inside.
It was necessary that he surrender.
And that took time.
I'm going to go.
For almost seven hours,
the people entered into a coup and it turned into a revolution.
The very day after the revolution,
Adelino and his fellow journalists discovered a brand new world.
They could finally write freely.
This journal was not aimed at any censorship commission.
It is a rebellion against 48 years of censorship.
We didn't just learn to write.
To watch a newspaper,
or talk on the radio,
or show images on TV,
we had to learn to speak freely.
So how do you do it?
It's like learning to ride a bicycle.
But not all Portuguese people value the Carnation Revolution.
The far-right has re-emerged in the form of a new party,
Chega,
founded in 2019.
...is now the third largest force in the country.
It's seducing more and more young people.
Hi,
how are you?
Can you show me the last post?
Yes,
sir.
How many people are here?
112,000.
Federico Troppa believes the Carnation Revolution was a black day.
It was a good decolonization,
it was a betrayal.
We have a very forgotten theme in Portuguese history,
which are the returnees,
that is,
the Portuguese who were in Africa,
who were forgotten,
who were abandoned.
So it was a bad decolonization and today this D is the D of the uncontrolled of our borders,
with the uncontrolled immigration,
and on the other hand we have the
D of development that never reached Portugal.
Modern-day Portugal is one of the most dynamic economies in Europe.
Its GDP grew 2.3%
last year,
the envy of some of its neighbours.
But intense inequalities persist,
the cause of anger that Chega is tapping into.
Last March,
the party won 18%
of votes,
quadrupling its number of seats in the Lisbon Parliament,
a breakthrough achieved by some very young MPs.
Well guys,
today we have the first intervention of Madalena Cordeiro who is going to blow up and break everything.
How are you more or less prepared for today?
I'm a little nervous for being the first one,
but...
You're going to do it.
At just
25, Rita Matias is the face of the young.
She's well aware that 50 years after the revolution,
many Portuguese people fear the return of the far right.
We have xenophobic messages,
racist messages,
fascist messages,
a set of meanings that are not translated into the reality of our proposals.
What we are defending is common sense,
what people say on the streets,
in the cafes,
in the restaurants.
So,
at the end of the day,
this fear is made up by those who don't want to see reforms,
who don't want to see their privileges.
Fifty years after it happened,
the symbolic Carnation Revolution is no longer sacrosanct.
To avoid the mistakes of the past being repeated,
the descendants of the April captains are also taking a role in politics.
So,
uncle...
Carlos'
nephew,
Tiago,
is in the process of setting up his own party.
Today,
some of these rights can be threatened,
such as the rights of women.
There are already groups that defend,
for example,
the deregulation of the voluntary pregnancy interruption.
It goes back.
We have to fight it.
and somehow try to keep these rights that have been conquered in the last 50 years from going back.
nation revolution won't live forever.
They hope the memory of that turning point will live on in the spirit of the Portuguese people.